Okay, so in this video then, let us
discuss the basic components of a contract.
Now, in order to have a contract, a
contract has to have five basic elements.
There are five basic elements in every
contract.
Now, typically a contract has many,
many more, there's many components of a
contract, but in order to
actually have a contract, these
are the five basic components,
the ones listed here.
An offer, an acceptance, capacity,
consideration and a legal purpose.
So let's go through each one then.
An offer.
What good or service is a seller offering
that has to be written in the contract?
What good or service is the seller
offering or the vendor?
Then the acceptance.
What good or service is the buyer
accepting?
That has to mirror the original offer.
The buyer has to accept what the vendor is
offering or what the seller is offering.
So that is the acceptance.
And then plus, what's the acceptance
criteria?
Again, documented as part of the contract.
So you have the offer, you have the
acceptance, then have the capacity.
Capacity means a couple of things here.
First of all, the seller has
the appropriate authority,
appropriate capacity to
actually perform the work.
They have the appropriate licensers and
certifications if needed, right,
to actually perform the work.
And then plus, they're a legal entity.
So whoever is performing the work,
right, they are a legal entity,
the organization is a legal entity.
And they can perform the work in this
particular environment.
They're a solvent organization.
And then plus all the other legal jargon
that goes behind that, people that are
signing the contract are
authorized, right, from behalf of
the organization to make
decisions and sign the contract.
Plus, there are sound mind, legal age,
and so and so forth.
So that's what capacity refers to.
Then you have the consideration.
And consideration is something for
something.
The seller is providing this good or
service for something in return.
Normally it's money, but it doesn't have
to be.
Another name for that is quid pro quo.
That's what quid pro quo means.
Basically something for something.
So the seller is providing this good or
service for something in return now most
of the time with you know it's money but
like said it doesn't have to be and then a
legal purpose right so this good or
service that the seller is providing is a
legal good or service in the locale where
it's been provided so whether it's in the
country whether it's in the state whether
it's in the province right or whether it's
in the village in the town it's legal
right so that's a very simple example,
let's say, you know, while we're in the
subject of building a house, right,
I ask you to build me a house,
right, you're my builder, I ask you to
build me a house, I
tell you, I want you to
build this 200 foot tower in my backyard.
Well, that might be illegal in my town.
That might be illegal in my village,
right, or in my locale, right?
So you and I will not be
able to have a contract
for you to build this 200
foot tower in my backyard.
There may be zoning, restrictions.
So a contract then has to be for a legal
purpose.
So these are five basic elements of a
contract.
Now, there are a couple of other
components of a contract.
And this is not an exhaustive list by any
means, but these are just some additional
components that you will
see, you know, just some
common components that
you also see in a contract.
I mean, there's many, many components that
you would see typically in a contract.
So the schedule and the delivery date.
So when is the final delivery going to be
of this particular product, whatever the
seller is delivering, right, whether it's
a product or a service?
Right.
And then what are all the different
milestones in between?
Right.
And then what's the basic schedule of
these milestones?
So that could be written in a contract.
Plus what's the responsibility of both
parties, buyer and seller.
So buyer, for example, or rather the
seller, for example, cannot perform the
work until the buyer has given
them enough information or
they've provided the appropriate
tools for them to do the work.
So, again, that's all, you know,
whose responsibility is what?
That's going to be documented in the
contract as well.
And then any kind of guarantee and warranty
that the seller might be providing.
And then along with the responsibilities,
you've got the authority as well,
the authority of who is going to be
signing off on the deliverable,
for example, who is going to be testing
the deliverable, and so on and so forth.
Termination, we're going to talk about
termination in a separate video,
but what are the provisions for that?
Again, that could be documented in the
contract as well.
And then depending on the type of
contract, there might be some incentive.
So we're going to talk about the different
types of contracts, and different types of
contracts have, you know, some have
incentive, incentive fees, penalties,
and so and so forth.
And then any kind of terms and conditions,
right?
So on terms and conditions itself is a
huge topic.
You don't necessarily need to know all of
them for the PMB exam, but that in itself
is a huge section, typically on a
contract.
So these are the basic elements then of a
So you have the five basic elements that
we just discussed.
the previous slide, the
offer, the acceptance,
the capacity,
consideration, legal purpose.
And these are just some,
just a few of the additional
components that you
often see in a contract.
Again, not an exhaustive list by any
means.
There's many, many, many items that can go
into a contract.